Guide to the Charles Robert Leslie Collection
Yale Center for British Art, Rare Books and Manuscripts
- Correspondence, Series III
  - Mary Leslie
    - Letter to Charles Robert Leslie, probably 1851 or 1852, July 18; Leslie, Mary, 1833-1907; 4 pages (1 folded leaf); 18 x 22 cm. Autograph letter, illustrated and signed; written in pen and brown/black ink with watercolor and pen and ink illustration. (Box 1, Folder 47)
      Mary writes while on a visit to her brother, Bradford, who was at this time working as an engineer on a bridge in Chepstow, Wales. She reports that Bradford has taken her to Wyndcliff. She describes the beautiful view and includes a small watercolor illustration to show the rainbow that appeared after "a heavy storm" from which she and Bradford were forced to seek shelter while sketching. She writes of observing the robins in the area. She expresses sympathy about her mother's toothache (about which she has heard from her sister, Caroline) and about an unsuccessful party that her parents have had. She requests "some small good oil colour paint brushes," and illustrates the five brushes in pen and ink.
      Correspondence; Leslie, Charles Robert, 1794-1859 -- Correspondence; Leslie, Mary, 1833-1907 -- Correspondence
    - Letter to Harriet Stone Leslie, probably 1851 or 1852; Leslie, Mary, 1833-1907; 4 pages (1 folded leaf); 18 x 22 cm. Autograph letter, signed and illustrated; written in pen and brown/black ink. (Box 1, Folder 48)
      Mary writes to her mother, relaying a "funny story" that she says is related to one that her sister Caroline has included in a recent letter to Bradford. The story concerns a little girl who had her pet sparrows baked into a pudding for her birthday. The rather macabre tale, Mary reflects, is "not such a funny one as Caroline's, but it sounded much better than I can write it." Mary writes about her drawing habits of late, copying faces out of books by Chalon and Lewis. She reports on a fair in Chepstow, which she is missing because of the rain. She also writes of visiting the grounds of the estate of the Phillipses, a local family. She includes two pen and ink vignettes--one of birds decorating a vase of flowers with string and a sketch of the fair.
    - Letter to Harriet Stone Leslie, probably 1851 or 1852; Leslie, Mary, 1833-1907; 1 page (1 leaf); 6 x 11.2 cm. Fragment of an autograph letter, written in pen and brown/black ink and illustrated in watercolor. (Box 1, Folder 49)
      A watercolor illustration remains on this fragment of a letter from Mary Leslie to her mother. The illustration shows a man dressed in a sort of 17th century military costume sitting high in a tree. The letter has been cut down so that only the fragment with the illustration remains. The handwriting that is visible and the style of letter seems similar to those found in Mary's letters home from Chepstow, in 1851-2.
  - Robert Charles Leslie
    - Letter to Charles Robert Leslie, 1841; Leslie, Robert Charles, 1826-; 2 pages (1 leaf); 22.5 x 18.5 cm. Autograph letter, signed; written in pen and brown/black ink. (Box 1, Folder 50)
      Robert Charles writes to his father from New York, commenting excitedly on his location and its proximity to water. He appears to have been staying at West Point, with his uncle and aunt. Robert writes of boarding the "Hendrick Hudson" and watching ships in the area. Robert is pleased with West Point and remarks that faculty members recall him from the family's earlier stay at West Point in 1833. Robert tells his father that today "went to see all the principle New York Artists viz Mr. West, Mr. Huntington & Mr. Darand, very cilvil [sic] all of them." Robert remarks that he will be home soon and closes with a commentary on the constant local noise of "fire engines...of night bells tolling men shouting & engines running...[I]t seems to me they have a great many fires..."
      Although this letter is undated, R.C. Leslie's 1894 autobiographical work, A Waterbiography, mentions a trip to America in 1841, in order to study ships and their construction.
      Correspondence; Leslie, Charles Robert, 1794-1859 -- Correspondence; Leslie, Robert Charles, 1826- -- Correspondence
    - Letter to Charles Robert Leslie, 1844 September 7; Leslie, Robert Charles, 1826-; 2 pages (1 leaf); 23.5 x 19 cm. Autograph letter, signed; written in pen and brown/black ink. (Box 1, Folder 51)
      Robert writes to his father, commenting on the warm and pleasant weather. He discusses going out to make sketches, acknowledging that a sketching case (that his parents presumably gave him) works well but requesting "a little vermillion in a letter." Robert remarks that "Mr. Wallis has offered to let us have the small boat belonging to his cutter whenever we want a boat inside the harbour." He sends his brother George's love to the family.
    - Letter to Charles Robert Leslie, 1845 January 22; Leslie, Robert Charles, 1826-; 1 page (1 leaf); 25 x 20 cm. Autograph letter, signed; written in pen and brown/black ink. (Box 1, Folder 52)
      Robert writes a brief letter with news of his sea voyage, stating that he is "off the Lizard, dead wind, Falmouth Pilot aboard, can't say when we shall be in London..." Robert adds a brief postscript to indicate that his Aunt Anne will land at Portsmouth in a few days. The letter is addressed to "Charles Leslie, Esq'r RA" at 12 Pine Apple Place, Edgware, London.
  - Daniel Maclise
    - Letter to an unidentified recipient, 1860 June 11; Maclise, Daniel, 1806-1870; 1 page (1 leaf); 15 x 10 cm. Autograph letter, signed; written in pen and brown/black ink. (Box 1, Folder 53)
      Maclise writes: "I am very much obliged by your kind present [?] of the Autobiography of Leslie which seems a most readable book and one that I shall peruse with great interest."
      The present letter was removed from the library's copy of Autobiographical recollections. Presumably this copy previously belonged to the painter Daniel Maclise.
      Correspondence; Leslie, Charles Robert, 1794-1859; Maclise, Daniel, 1806-1870 -- Correspondence
  - Peter Powell
    - Letter to Charles Robert Leslie, 1826? July 7; Powell, Peter, circa 1775-1855; 3 pages (1 folded leaf); 18 x 23 cm. Autograph letter, signed; written in pen and brown/black ink. (Box 1, Folder 54)
      Powell writes to chide Leslie for not having conveyed his news about the birth of his child (likely Robert, born in 1826) to Powell. He notes, humorously, that Leslie had asked him not to come back to his home until after the baby was born, but that Leslie has forgotten to tell Powell of the birth, despite having given other friends the news. Powell sends his congratulations and adds a postscript about seeing Constable the previous day.
      Correspondence; Powell, Peter, circa 1775-1855 -- Correspondence; Leslie, Charles Robert, 1794-1859 -- Correspondence
    - Letter to Charles Robert Leslie, 1827 February 5; Powell, Peter, circa 1775-1855; 4 pages (1 folded leaf); 24.5 x 38 cm. Autograph letter, signed; written in pen and brown/black ink. (Box 1, Folder 55)
      Powell writes from Rue de Grenelle, Paris, to Leslie at Lisson Grove, Paddington. Powell apologizes for being so bad about correspondence, blaming his own procrastination for this problem as well as for his failure to marry. He acknowledges Leslie's relatively recent marriage and the birth of his son Robert. Powell remarks that his trip to Italy is postponed and he will be staying in Paris for the spring. He comments on the death of the artist John Flaxman (1755-1826), and discusses affairs of the Royal Academy, among them being whether the Academy will elect Constable to be "the new member in the room of Flaxman," saying that if Constable is not elected, the Academy can "go to the Devil..." He goes on to note that it seems Newton "is getting on very well with his Picture from Gil Blas," but that he does not know what Leslie's latest project is. He closes with a wish that he and Leslie were more alike, and asks about mutual acquaintances and domestic news.
      Correspondence; Powell, Peter, circa 1775-1855 -- Correspondence; Leslie, Charles Robert, 1794-1859 -- Correspondence; Royal Academy of Arts (Great Britain)
    - Letter to Charles Robert Leslie, 1827 November 27; Powell, Peter, circa 1775-1855; 4 pages (1 folded leaf); 24 x 38 cm. Autograph letter, signed; written in pen and brown/black ink. (Box 1, Folder 56)
      Powell writes from Padua to Leslie at Lisson Grove, Paddington. Powell writes in his usual jovial tone, discussing the pleasures of Italy and its comfortable climate. He imagines that Leslie has heard about him through "John Chalon who I met at Geneva and with whom I afterwards visited the Valley of Chamonix & the celebrated Mont Blanc." Powell goes on discussing various people whom he has met in cities around Italy. He notes that he has heard about the Royal Academy Exhibition, saying that Leslie has won "poor Collins's generous heart for ever I understand." He describes traveling in Italy with the Callcotts and meeting a painter called Mr. Lewis. He also describes a chapel painted by Giotto, in good condition thanks, in part, to being preserved from destruction by Napoleon. He urges Leslie to see the chapel. Powell closes by mentioning several mutual friends, among them Newton, the Condeys [?], and Constable.
    - Letter to Charles Robert Leslie, 1829 November 30; Powell, Peter, circa 1775-1855; 2 pages (1 leaf); 26 x 22 cm. Autograph letter, signed; written in pen and brown/black ink. (Box 1, Folder 57)
      Powell writes from No. 68 Via Sistina, Rome, to Leslie at Portman Place, Edgware Road, London. Powell writes romantically of his difficulty in leaving Rome, discussing its staggering history. He compares the relative freedom of Rome's citizens to the oppressions of English life, with its "noise & newspapers & cant about liberty..." He writes that, in his two years in Rome, there has only been one execution and "that for murder!" He goes on to talk about a mutual acquaintance who is traveling for his health, and notes having seen a print of "your Duke and Duchess," a work by Leslie, in a periodical. Powell concludes buoyantly with remarks about never wanting to return to England, despite the failure of some of his friendships because of his long time away.
    - Letter to Charles Robert Leslie, 1838 October 26; Powell, Peter, circa 1775-1855; 4 pages (1 folded leaf); 22.5 x 37 cm. Autograph letter, signed; written in pen and brown/black ink. (Box 1, Folder 58)
      Powell writes from Clapham Rise and addresses the letter to Leslie at Pine Apple Place, Edgware Road, London. He reports on his recent "Ramble through Belgium" and is sorry to have missed an invitation from Leslie to dine with him. He offers to attend another dinner to make "the best amends." He wants to see how Leslie is coming along with his "Coronation Picture, having met with two of your Lady Sitters at Tunbridge Wells last week." Peter closes with a rather cryptic postscript about a decision being made about a Jane Gamble. He is concerned about her leaving her home (?), saying that her parents will never recover from it.
    - Letter to Charles Robert Leslie, 1840 February 6; Powell, Peter, circa 1775-1855; 4 pages (1 folded leaf); 31 x 38 cm. Autograph letter, signed; written in pen and brown/black ink. (Box 1, Folder 59)
      Powell writes from Edinburgh, apologizing for his lack of correspondence. He notes that he never expected to stay in Edinburgh past the previous October, but reports that he has been staying with some "Batchelor Friends" who are also artists, and could not leave the lovely setting in which he stayed. This setting featured a castle, "river, hills, lake," etc., and "afforded a delightful ramble..." He writes, rather humorously, of narrowly avoiding marriage to a local woman and of hosting a church service in the Hall where he is staying. He writes Leslie that "your Picture has been exhibiting here with great eclat, & prints to the amount of three hundred Pounds subscribed for in...two days." He writes of meeting a Mr. Allan, R.A., and plans on returning to England within the month.